불과 열의 사용법을 터득한 것은
인류 문명 최대의 업적으로 일컬어진다
The greatest triumph of civilization is often seen as our mastery of heat.
하지만 냉기의 정복도
그에 못지 않은 장엄한 여정이다
Yet our conquest of cold is an equally epic journey
그 시작은 어두웠으나, 마침내
첨단의 극저온 기술에 이르렀다
from dark beginnings to an ultracool frontier.
과거 수 세기 동안
냉기는 곤혹스러운 수수께끼였다
For centuries, cold remained a perplexing mystery.
누구도 그 실체를 이해하지 못했으며
Nobody had any idea what it was,
이것을 이용한다는 것은
더욱 힘들었다
much less how to harness its effects.
그러나 최근 100년간, 냉기는
인간의 일과 생활을 바꾸어놓았다
Yet in the last hundred years, cold has transformed the way we live and work.
냉장고와 냉동식품이 없는
가정이나 슈퍼마켓,
Imagine homes or supermarkets without fridges and frozen foods,
냉방 시설이 없는 고층 건물,
or skyscrapers without air conditioning,
액체 산소를 이용하지 못하는 병원은
상상도 할 수 없게 되었다
or hospitals without liquid oxygen.
지금은 당연하게 여겨지는
냉기를 다루는 기술 덕분에
We take for granted the technology of cold,
밖으로는 우주를 탐사하고, 안으로는
우리의 뇌를 들여다볼 수 있게 되었다
yet it has enabled us to explore outer space and the inner depths of our brain.
또한, 최첨단 극저온 기술을 통한
양자 컴퓨터와 고속 네트워크는
And as we develop new ultracold technology
to create quantum computers and high speed networks,
인간이 사고하고 교류하는 방식마저
변화시키게 될 수도 있다
it may even change the way we think and interact.
이것은 지난 4세기에 걸쳐
과학자와 몽상가들이
This is the story of how scientists and dreamers over the past four centuries
점점 더 낮은 온도를
만들어내기 위해 뛰어들어
plunged lower and lower down the temperature scale
냉기를 정복하고
우리의 삶을 풍요롭게 하며
to conquer the cold, enrich our lives
나아가 저온의 궁극적인 한계에
도전한 이야기이다
and attempt to reach the ultimate limits of cold,
빛의 속도만큼이나 따라잡기 힘든,
성배와도 같은 이 한계점은
a holy grail as elusive as the speed limits of light.
절대 영도이다
Absolute zero.
절대 영도 - 1부: 냉기를 정복하다
(2007.7.24 BBC Four)
극한의 추위는 인간의 상상력에서
늘 특별한 자리를 차지했다
Extreme cold has always held a special place in our imagination.
오랜 세월 동안, 추위는
죽음과 어둠을 몰고 다니는
For thousands of years, it seemed like a malevolent force
사악한 힘으로 여겨졌다
associated with death and darkness.
냉기는 설명할 수 없는 현상이었다
Cold was an unexplained phenomenon.
그것은 과연 물질인가, 과정인가,
아니면 어떤 특별한 존재인가?
Was it a substance, a process or some special state of being?
17세기에는 아무도 알지 못했다
Back in the 17th century, no one knew.
그래도 런던의 쌀쌀한 겨울 날씨에서
냉기의 영향만큼은 확실히 느껴졌다
But they certainly felt its effects in the freezing London winters.
17세기 영국은 소위 소빙기(小氷期)*의
한복판에 있었습니다
* 16~19세기 북반구 기온이 낮아졌던 시기
17th century England was in the middle of what's now called the Little Ice Age.
요즘 기준으로는
환상적으로 추운 날씨였죠
It was fantastically cold by modern standards.
사이먼 샤퍼 - 케임브리지 대학
불이 아니었다면 대부분의 사람들에게
거의 언제나 추운 세상이었죠
You have to imagine a world lit by fire in which most people are cold most of the time.
추위는 그 자체로
어떤 실재감을 주었고,
Cold would have felt like a real presence,
사람들이 느낄 수 있고
실체가 있는 존재처럼 보였습니다
a kind of positive agent that was affecting how people felt.
이것은 고대 그리스의
아리스토텔레스 이래로 이어진
And that fit it nicely with the most orthodox received view
자연철학의 가장 정통적인 견해와
잘 들어맞았습니다
that natural philosophers had inherit from the Greeks, from Aristotle, hundreds of years earlier,
그것은, 열과 냉기라는
두 존재가 있다는 것입니다
that there are two agents in the world,
hot and cold,
둘의 기능은 대칭적이죠
they function symmetrically,
서로 합쳐질수도, 나눠질수도 있습니다
they can combine or separate.
그때의 사람들은
추위에 손쓸 도리가 없었다
Back then, people felt at the mercy of cold.
자연의 힘을 신의 행위로 간주하며
두려워하던 시대였기 때문이다
This was a time when such natural forces were viewed with awe, as acts of god.
감히 냉기를 가지고 장난치는 사람은
스스로 위험을 감수해야만 했다
So anyone attempting to tamper with cold did so at their peril.
이를 최초로 시도한 사람은
연금술사 코넬리우스 드레블이었다
The first to try was an alchemist Cornelius Drebbel.
1620년 어느 더운 여름날,
제임스 1세 왕과 그의 측근들이
On a hot summer's day in 1620, King James I and his entourage
기상천외한 사건을
체험하기 위해 도착했다
arrived to experience an unearthly event.
궁정 마술사이기도 했던 드레블은
Drebbel, who was also the court magician,
여름을 겨울로 둔갑시켜 보이겠다며
왕에게 호언장담했다
had a wager with the king that he could turn summer into winter.
그는 실내 공간으로는
영국 제도에서 가장 큰 곳인
He would attempt to chill the air in the largest interior space in the British Isles,
웨스트민스터 홀의 공기를
냉각시킬 계획이었다
the Great Hall of Westminster.
드레블은 왕을 뼛속까지
벌벌 떨게 만들 심산이었다
Drebbel hoped to shake the king to his core.
그는 놀랄만큼 창의력이 풍부한
빼어난 발명가였습니다
He had a phenomenally fertile mind. He was an inventor par excellence.
연금술, 영구기관,
시간, 공간, 행성, 달, 태양, 신, ..
His whole world was steeped in a world of alchemy, of perpetual motion machines,
앤드류 쉬들로
이런 주제에 깊이 몰두해 있었죠
of the idea of time, space, planets, Moon, Sun, Gods.
열렬한 종교인이었구요
He was a fervently religious man.
그는 자연 속에서 셀수없이 많은
가능성을 찾아냈던 사람이었습니다
He was a person for whom nature presented a phenomenal.. a galaxy of possibilities.
평생 드레블에 대해 큰 흥미를 가졌던
화학자 앤드류 쉬들로 박사는
Dr. Andrew Szydlo, a chemist with a lifelong fascination for Drebbel,
이 뛰어난 궁정 마술사의 마법을
직접 재현해 보려고 한다
enjoys his reincarnation as the great court magician.
대부분의 연금술사들처럼,
드레블은 트릭을 공개하지 않았다
Like most alchemists, Drebbel kept his methods secret.
쉬들로는 드레블이 인공 추위를 만들어낸
수법에 대한 자신의 추측을 시험하려 한다
Dr. Szydlo wants to test his ideas on how Drebbel created artificial cold.
드레블이 최대한 낮은 온도를
만들어내려고 시도했을 때
When Drebbel was trying to achieve the lowest temperature possible
그는 일반적으로 얻을 수 있는
최저 온도는 얼음이라는걸 알았습니다
he knew that ice, of course, was the freezing point, the coldest you could get normally.
얼음을 다른 종류의 소금과 섞으면
더 낮은 온도까지 내려간다는 사실도
But he would have been aware of the facts, through his experience,
that mixing ice with different salts could get you a colder temperature.
경험적으로 알고 있었을 것입니다
소금은 물의 어는점을
낮추는 효과가 있다
Salts will lower the temperature at which ice melts.
쉬들로 박사는 드레블이 소금을 이용하여
온도를 떨어뜨렸을거라고 추측한다
Dr. Szydlo thinks Drebbel probably used common table salt
which gives the biggest temperature drop.
그러나 소금과 얼음만으로는
그 넓은 공간의 기온을 낮추기엔 역부족이다
But salt and ice alone would not be enough to cool down such a large interior.
드레블은 정교한 기계장치를
만드는 솜씨로 유명했다
Drebbel was famous for designing elaborate contraptions,
쉬들로 박사는 드레블이 사용했을
장치에 대한 아이디어를 갖고 있다
a passion shared by Dr. Szydlo, who has an idea for the alchemist's machine.
여기 이렇게 송풍기를 달아서
So here, we would've had a fan which would've been turned over,
따뜻한 공기를
이 차가운 용기 위로 보냅니다
blowing warm air over the cold vessels there.
공기가 차가운 용기 위를 지나면서
And as the air blows over these cold jars,
이것은 사실상 세계 최초의
에어컨이 되는 것입니다
we would have had in effect the world's first air conditioning unit.
하지만, 정말 이것으로
여름을 겨울로 바꿀 수 있었을까?
But could this really turn summer into winter?
단 5초만에 최대한 잘 섞어야 합니다
The idea is to stir it in as well as possible, in the five seconds that you have to do it.
쉬들로 박사는
이 혼합물 용기들을 쌓아서
Dr. Szydlo stacks the jars of freezing mixture
공기가 이 차가운 구간을
통과하게 하려고 한다
to create cold corridors for the air to pass through.
공기가 아주 차갑네요
Now we can feel it's very cold.
찬 공기가 손에 떨어지는 것을
느낄 수 있습니다
In fact I could feel cold air actually falling on my hands
찬 공기가 따뜻한 공기보다
무거우니까요
because cold air of course is denser than warm air
손의 감촉으로
확실하게 느껴집니다
and one can feel it quite clearly on the fingers.
과연, 따뜻한 바람이
지나가면서 차가워질 것인가?
The vital question, "Would the gust of warm air become cold?"
커버를 두장째 벗겨내니까
확실히 찬바람이 와 닿는군요
I can feel certainly a blast of cold air hitting me as that second cover was released.
현재 온도 14도입니다
Well, temperature.. we're on 14 at the moment.
계속 해 주세요.
지금 잘 하고 있어요
Yes, keep it going. That's definitely the right direction.
아마 아직도 좀더..
I think possibly even closer still, we'll..
인공적인 추위를 경험한
왕의 반응은 어땠을까?
So how would the king have reacted to his encounter with man-made cold?
깜짝 놀랐겠죠.
어찌된 영문인지 몰랐을 겁니다
He would have been shocked. He wouldn't have known what was happening.
신이나 악마의 힘을 빌린건 아닐까
하는 의문을 가졌을 법도 합니다
He could have in fact been wondering whether they were some action of God's
or some sort of demonological forces which were in action.
말 그대로 오싹한 한기를 느끼며
황급히 자리를 뜨지 않았을까요
And he would have left hastily, freezing, as he did so.
드레블이 그 방법에 대해
기록해 두었더라면
Had Drebbel written up his great stunt,
냉방 기술의 발명자로
역사에 기록되었을 것이다
he might have gone down in history as the inventor of air conditioning.
그러나 이 아이디어는
3세기가 지나서야 다시 빛을 보았다
Yet it would be almost three centuries before this idea eventually took off.
냉기를 파악하고 정복하기 위해서는
전혀 새로운 사고방식이 필요했다
To advance knowledge and conquer the cold required man with a very different mindset.
제임스 왕 밑의 대법관이었던
프랜시스 베이컨은
King James' Lord Chancellor Francis Bacon
과학적 방법론을 구사하여
열과 냉기를 연구한 최초의 인물이다
was the first to apply the scientific method to the study of heat and cold.
그는 고대로부터 내려오는
지식을 답습하는 대신
He believed it was important to conduct experiments and analyze the results
실험을 하고 그 결과를 분석하는
연구 방법의 중요성을 깨달았다
rather than rely on the established wisdom of the ancients.
프랜시스 베이컨에게, 열과 냉기는
세계관의 핵심에 놓인 문제였습니다
For Francis Bacon, heat and cold turned out to be right at the center of his world view.
열과 냉기가 인간에게 얼마나 중요한지
생각해 보면 그 까닭을 알 수 있습니다
One way of understanding why that's so is think why heat and cold matter to human beings.
17세기에는 특히나
두 가지 이유로 중요했는데
They really matter in the 17th century for two reasons.
날씨, 그리고 질병입니다
One is the weather, and one is disease.
사실 일상생활에서 보면,
따뜻함이 건강에 주는 영향과
There was after all an obvious tension in everyday experience
차가움이 건강에 주는 영향 사이의
팽팽한 긴장이 존재합니다
between the healthy effects of warmth and healthy effects of cold.
따뜻함은 건강을 유지시켜 줍니다.
생기가 달아나 버리지 않게 돕죠
Warmth made you healthy because it stopped you radiating away the vital spirits within you.
그런데, 차가움도 죽음에 맞서는
중요한 역할을 합니다
But cold obviously had crucial effects against death as well.
차갑게 유지되는 물질은
썩지 않고 오래 보존되지요
It could preserve things for immensely long times,
물론 프랜시스 베이컨의 육체도
예외는 아니겠죠
and maybe it could preserve Francis Bacon's body too.
베이컨은 자신이 직접
실험을 하는 경우는 드물었다
Bacon rarely carried out experiments himself.
그런데 그 몇 안되는 실험 중 하나가
그에게 불행을 가져다 주었다
But his one foray into the preservative effects of the cold had disastrous consequences.
그는 방금 잡은 닭에
얼음과 눈을 채워서
He took a freshly killed chicken and stuffed it full of ice and snow
닭고기가 얼마나 오래
신선하게 보존되는지 조사했다
to investigate how much longer the chicken meats might stay fresh.
그 결과는 놀라웠다
He was impressed by the results.
닭고기는 며칠간이나
신선하게 유지된 것이다
The chicken did remain fresh for many days.
하지만 불운하게도,
추위에 몸을 내맡긴 탓에
Unfortunately, during the process of exposing his own body to the cold
그는 폐렴에 걸리고 말았다
he caught pneumonia.
베이컨은 병상에서 죽어 가며
As Bacon lay dying, it dawned on him that
냉기에 대한 호기심의 대가가
그의 목숨이었음을 깨달았다
his fascination with the cold was going to cost him his life.
그의 실험은 아이러니한
비극으로 끝났지만,
The irony, tragedy of that rather sad experiment didn't dissuade his followers
얼음이나 눈의 냉장 효과를 실험하려는
후학들의 열의는 꺾이지 않았습니다
from doing more experiments on ice, and snow, and its vital or preservative effects.
베이컨의 뒤를 따른 학자들은
The men who followed Bacon were really convinced that
운동, 열, 냉기 등을
종합적으로 이해할 수 있다면
if we could understand the way in which motion, cold and heat fitted together
인간을 질병에서 해방시키고
자연의 비밀을 풀게 될거라고 확신했습니다
we could save ourselves from diseases, we could unlock the mysteries of the universe.
"냉기란 무엇인가?"
이 근본적인 질문은
This fundamental question, "What is cold?"
베이컨이 사망한 이듬해에 태어난
로버트 보일을 사로잡았다
haunted Robert Boyle who was born the year after Bacon died.
부유한 귀족인 초대 코크 백작의
아들이었던 그는
The son of the Earl of Cork, a wealthy nobleman,
사비를 들여 값비싼 실험실을
차릴 수 있었다
Boyle used his fortune to build an extensive laboratory.
보일은 공기의 성질에 대한
실험으로 유명하지만
Boyle is famous for his experiments on the nature of air.
냉기의 비밀을 터득한
최초의 학자이기도 했다
But he also became the first master of cold.
이것이 중요성에 비해 외면받은 주제라고
판단한 그는, 수많은 관련 실험을 했다
Believing it to be an important but neglected subject, he carried out hundreds of experiments.
그는 냉기의 정체에 대한 관념들을
매우 체계적으로 검증했습니다
He worked through, very systematically, a series of ideas about what cold is.
이것은 공기로부터 나오는가?
Does it come from the air?
이것은 빛의 부재에 기인한 것인가?
Does it come from the absence of light?
냉기를 불러일으키는 특이한 입자
같은 것들이 존재하는 것인가?
Is it that there are strange so-called 'frigorific' cold-making particles?
보일은 그 시대의 가장 유력한
견해를 공박했는데
The dominant view certainly in Boyle's lifetime,
어떤 견해이냐면, 냉기는
어떤 근원적인 물질이라는 생각입니다
the view that he set out to attack, is that cold is a primordial substance,
즉, 몸이 이 물질을 빨아들이면
체온이 떨어지고
that when bodies get colder, they're sucking in this primordial cold.
이를 방출하면
체온이 올라간다는거죠
and as they get warmer, they expel it.
그는 이 관점이 틀렸다고 생각하고,
실험을 통해 반증하려고 했습니다
Boyle thought that was wrong, and he did experiments to show that it was wrong.
보일은 물이 얼 때 부피가 늘어나는
현상에 대해 의문을 가지고
Boyle was curious about the way water expanded when it turned to ice.
부피가 늘어나면서 무게도 함께
증가하는지 알아보려고 했다
He wondered whether the increase in volume was accompanied by an increase in weight.
물을 채운 통의 무게를 정확히 잰 다음
눈밭으로 가지고 나가서
They carefully weighted a barrel of water and took it outside in the snow,
밤새 얼게 했다
leaving it to freeze overnight.
보일은, 물이 얼음이 되었을 때
무게가 늘어난다면
Boyle reasoned that if once the water turned to ice, the barrel weighed more,
아마도 냉기가 물질임을 보여주는
근거가 될거라고 추론했다
then perhaps cold was a substance after all.
그러나 무게를 재어 보니
조금도 차이가 없었다
But when they re-weighed the barrel, they discovered it weighed exactly the same.
이를 보고 보일이 추측한 것은
So what must be happening, Boyle guessed,
팽창이란 것은 물의 입자들이
점점 거리를 넓힌 것이지,
was that the particles of water were moving further apart,
외부에서 물질이 유입되는게
아니라는 논리였습니다
that was the expansion, not some substance flowing into the barrel from outside.
보일은 냉기가 물질이 아니라
입자들에 일어나는 일종의 현상이라는
Boyle was becoming increasingly convinced that cold was not a substance
생각을 갈수록 굳히게 되었다
but something that was happening to the particles,
그는 이전에 했던
공기 펌프 실험을 상기했다
and began to think back to his earlier experiments with his air pump.
보일은 용기에 든 공기 입자들이
탄성이 있어서 튕긴다고 생각했습니다
Boyle's idea was that the air trapped in this glass container is springing, it's elastic.
공기를 압축하면
반발한다는 것이죠
As you try and compress it, it resists.
이러한 생각은 열과 냉기에 대한
그의 연구와도 깊은 연관이 있습니다
Now this is very closely linked in Boyle's program to the way he studies heat and cold.
공기와 같은 물질은
온도가 올라가면 팽창하는데,
'cause his idea was that as substances like the air get warmer, they tend to expand.
그는 공기 입자를 아주 작은 용수철에
비유하여 이를 설명했습니다
It's as though the little particles, little springs..
out of which he had imagined each air particle is made,
온도가 올라가면 용수철이 풀리면서
더 많은 공간을 차지하니까 공기는 팽창합니다
gradually unwinding, so they take up more space, and they expand.
열은 특정한 형태의 운동이라는게
보일의 결론이었습니다
Boyle's conclusion here was that heat is a form of motion of a particular kind,
따라서 물질이 냉각되면
운동은 줄어들겠죠
and that as bodies cool down they move less and less.
가장 오래 출간된 보일의 저서는
냉기에 대한 책이었다
Boyle's longest published book was on the cold,
그럼에도 불구하고 이 주제는
무척이나 난해했던지,
yet he found its study troublesome and full of hardships,
보일은 자신이 마치
의료 도구나 의약품도 없이
declaring that he felt like a physician trying to work in a remote country
머나먼 땅에서 일하는 의사가 된
심정이라고 토로하기도 했다
without the benefit of instruments or medicines.
이 머나먼 동토에서 일하는데 있어
To properly explore this country of the cold,
그가 갈급히 원했던 중요한 도구는
정확한 온도계였다
Boyle lamented the lack of a vital tool, an accurate thermometer.
17세기 중반이 되어서야
It was not until the mid-17th century
피렌체의 유리 가공업자들이
정확히 조정된 온도계를 만들어냈다
that glass blowers in Florence began to produce accurately calibrated thermometers.
이제 온도의 측정이
가능해진 것이다
Now it became possible to measure degrees of hot and cold.
수은 대신 그보다 가벼운
알코올을 사용했기 때문에
Because rather than mercury they used alcohol which is much lighter,
그들이 만든 온도계 중에는
길이가 몇미터에 이르거나
they made thermometers that were sometimes several meters long,
나선형으로 꼬인 것들도 많았다
and more often wound into spirals.
그러나 아직도, 모든 온도계에는
하나의 커다란 문제점이 있었다
But there was still one major problem with all thermometers.
하나로 통일된 온도 체계가
존재하지 않았던 것이다
The lack of a universally agreed temperature scale.
장하석 - 런던 대학
온도에 숫자를 매기는 방식은
얼마든지 많이 있을 수 있죠
There are all kinds of different ways of
trying to stick numbers through these degrees of hot and cold and..
그래서 저마다 완전히
중구난방이었습니다
they, on the whole, didn't agree with each other at all.
피렌체에 있는 누군가는
이런 식의 온도계를,
So, one guy in Florence makes one kind of thermometer,
또 런던의 누군가는
다른 식의 온도계를..
another guy in London makes a different kind, and..
온도의 척도조차
통일되지 않았습니다
they just don't even have the same scale.
그래서 온도계를 표준화하는데
많은 어려움이 있었습니다
And so there was a lot of problem in trying to standardize thermometers.
온도 체계를 정한다고 해 봅시다.
어떻게 하면 될까요?
Imagine that you want to make a scaled of temperature. What do you do?
17~18세기 온도계 제작자나
실험가들도 잘 알고 있었던 것인데,
Well, the obvious thing to do, and this was well understood by
instrument makers and experimenters in the 17th and 18th century,
당연히 해결해야 하는 과제는
언제나 일정한 온도를 가지는
어떤 자연 현상을 찾아내어
is to try and find something in nature which you know always has the same temperature,
이것을 기준점으로 삼는 것입니다
and make that your fixed point.
그러한 자연 현상을
'두 개' 찾아낸다면 금상첨화죠
A better strategy even is to find 'two' such phenomena in nature.
좀더 차가운 아래쪽 기준점..
And then you have a lower fixed point, like something rather cold..
그리고 따뜻한 위쪽 기준점..
and an upper fixed point, something rather warm..
그리고 두 점 사이의
온도를 분할하여
and divide the degrees of temperature between
쓰기 편하게 100개 정도의
작은 단계로 쪼개는 것입니다
and decide 100 convenient bite-size chunks.
문제는, 그러한 현상을 어떻게
찾아내고 정의할 것인가 하는 겁니다
The problem however was to find, define, a phenomenon
whose temperature you guessed was fixed.
아래쪽 기준점으로는 얼음이
녹는 온도를 택할 수도 있겠죠
So for the lower fixed point, you might choose
the temperature of ice, just as it's melting.
이제 위쪽 기준점으로는
무수히 많은 후보들이 있습니다
And then there's an almost indefinite range of possible candidates
for your upper fixed point.
아이작 뉴턴은 소위 '열(熱)의 척도'를
정하기 위해 열심히 연구했습니다
Isaac Newton, for example, worked rather hard
on constructing what he called 'the scale of heat'.
그가 정의한 온도점은, 예를 들면
He for example defined the temperature
사람이 뜨거운 물에 손을 넣고
겨우 버틸 수 있는 온도..
which human can only just tolerate if they plunge their hand into warm water.
또는 사람의 겨드랑이 밑 온도..
사람의 혈액의 온도..
It could be the normal human underarm, the temperature of the human blood,
양초가 녹는 온도 등이었습니다
the temperature of wax just as it's melting.
널리 사용된 최초의 온도 체계는
다니엘 파렌하이트가 고안했다
The first temperature scale to be widely adopted was devised by Daniel Fahrenheit,
그는 네덜란드에서 의료용 온도계를
만든 숙련된 기구 제작자였다
an accomplished instrument maker who made thermometers for doctors in Holland.
그는 얼음, 물, 소금의 혼합물을 써서
기준점 0도를 잡고,
He used a mixture of ice, water, and salt for his zero degrees.
얼음이 녹는 온도는 32도,
Ice melting in water at 32 degrees.
그리고 사람의 체온을
위쪽 기준점 96도로 정했다
And for his upper fixed point, the temperature of the human body at 96 degrees,
이는 현재의 화씨 온도값과 거의 같다
(화씨 온도의 기준은 나중에 재조정되었음)
which is close to the modern value.
파렌하이트의 업적 가운데 하나는
One of the things that Fahrenheit was able to achieve was
수은을 써서 온도계의 크기를
확 줄인 것입니다
to make thermometers quite small, and that he did by using mercury,
이전의 다른 온도계는
알코올이나 공기를 이용했었죠
as opposed to alcohol or air which other people had used.
수은 온도계는 아주 작습니다
And because mercury thermometers are compact,
만일 온도계를
의료용으로 쓰려고 한다면
clearly if you're trying to use it for clinical purposes,
환자의 입에 큼지막한 온도계를
물릴 수는 없지 않겠습니까?
you don't want some big thing sticking out of the patient, so..
이런 작고 편리한 온도계를
보급한 덕분에
the fact that he could make them small and convenient,
파렌하이트의 명성과 영향력이
높아졌다고 생각합니다
that seems to be what made Fahrenheit so famous and so influential.
스웨덴의 천문학자
안데르스 셀시우스는
It was a Swedish astronomer Anders Celsius
온도 눈금을 100개로 분할하는
새로운 체계를 들고 나왔다
who came up with the idea of dividing the scale into 100 divisions.
셀시우스의 온도 체계는 원래
위아래가 뒤집힌 것이었습니다
The original scale used by Celsius was upside down.
다시 말해 물의 끓는점을 0도,
어는점을 100도로 정했습니다
So he had the boiling point of water as zero, and the freezing point as 100,
그리고 어는점 아래로 내려갈수록
온도값이 증가하는 식이죠
with numbers just continuing to increase as we go below freezing.
사실 이것은 온도계의 역사에서
풀리지 않는 작은 수수께끼입니다
And this is another little mystery
in the history of the thermometer that we just don't know for sure,
도대체 무슨 생각으로
그렇게 눈금을 매긴 것일까요?
What was he thinking when he labeled it this way?
그리고 몇년 뒤, 당시
스웨덴 학술원 원장이었던
And it was the botanist Linnaeus, who was then the president of the Swedish Academy who,
식물학자 린네가 나와서,
이런 말도 안되는 방식은 그만두자고
after a few years, said, "Well, we need to stop this nonsense!"
눈금을 뒤집어서 오늘날과 같은
섭씨 온도 체계를 확정했습니다
and inverted the scale to give us what we now call Celsius scale, today.
온도 체계가 만들어질 때만 해도
누구도 생각지 못했던 질문 하나는
A question nobody thought to ask when devising temperature scales was
"온도는 얼마까지 내려갈 수 있는가?
온도의 절대 하한은 있는가?" 이다
"How low can you go? Is there an absolute lower limit of temperature?"
절대 하한이 있을지도 모른다는 발상은
냉기의 역사에 전환점이 되었다
The idea that there might be, would become a turning point in the history of cold.
그 시초는 프랑스 물리학자
기욤 아몽통이었습니다
The story begins with the French physicist Guillaume Amontons.
그는 공기를 가열하고 냉각시키면서
팽창과 수축을 실험하던 중이었습니다
He was doing experiments heating and cooling bodies of air
to see how they expand and contract.
이제 공기 관 주위에 얼음을 놓고
지켜보겠습니다..
We're now going to put ice around the air bulb, and see what happens..
그는 공기를 냉각시키면 그 압력이나
부피가 줄어든다는 사실에 주목하고
And he was noticing that, well, when you cool a body of air
the volume or the pressure would go down.
계속해서 온도를 낮추면 어떻게 될까
추측해 보았습니다
And he speculated, "Well, what would happen if we just kept cooling it?"
온도와 압력의 그래프를 그려
By plotting temperature against pressure,
온도가 낮아지면
압력도 낮아짐을 알아냈고
Amontons saw that as the temperature dropped, so did the pressure.
이것으로부터 그는
놀라운 착상을 떠올렸다
And this gave him an extraordinary idea.
아몽통은 이런 가능성을 고려했습니다
Amontons started to consider the possibility,
이 선을 연장해서 압력이 0이 되는
지점까지 간다면 어떻게 될까?
"What would happen if you projected this line back until the pressure was zero?"
이것이 바로, 역사상 처음으로
And this was the first time in the course of history that
절대 온도 0도의 개념을
생각해 낸 사건이었습니다
people have actually considered the concept of an absolute zero of temperature,
압력 0, 온도 0인 지점이죠
zero pressure, zero temperature.
가만 생각해 보면
대단히 혁신적인 발상입니다
It was quite a revolutionary idea when you think about it,
왜냐면, 더 내려갈수 없는 온도의 하한이
있다는 생각을 하기는 쉽지 않습니다
because you wouldn't just think that temperature has a limit of lower bound, or zero,
위쪽으로는 얼마든지 더 뜨거워질수 있고
온도의 한계가 없으니까요
because in the upper end it can go on forever, we think, until it's hotter and hotter and hotter.
어쨌든 만약 이런 바닥점 0도가 있다면
But somehow, maybe there's a zero point where this all begins.
이 0도가 얼마나 낮은 온도인지
계산에 의해서 추정할 수 있습니다
So you could actually give a calculation of where this zero point would be.
그 계산은 아몽통 자신이 아니라
나중에 다른 사람들이 했죠
Amontons didn't do that calculation himself, but some other people did later on.
그 계산값은 오늘날 알고 있는 수치인
And when you do it, you get a value that's actually not that far from
섭씨 약 -273도에서
크게 벗어나지 않았습니다
the modern value of roughly -273 centigrade.
아몽통은 온도의 상한은 없지만
In one stroke, Amontons had realized that although temperatures might go on rising forever,
아래쪽으로는 절대 한계점이 있음을
즉시 알아차렸다
they could only fall as far as this absolute point.
그에게 이것은 이론적 한계점이었을뿐
실제로 시도할만한 목표는 아니었다
For him, this was a theoretical limit, not a goal to attempt to reach.
지구에서 가장 추운 곳보다도
훨씬 낮은 온도인
Before scientists could venture towards this zero point,
이 절대 영도를 향한 모험에 앞서서
far beyond the coldest temperatures on Earth,
반드시 해결해야 하는
근본적인 질문이 있었다
they needed to resolve a fundamental question.
이때의 과학자 대부분은, 냉기의 정체가
열(熱)의 부재라는 것을 알고 있었다
By now for most scientists, the penny had dropped.
The cold was simply the absence of heat.
그러나, 물질이 가열되거나 냉각될 때
어떤 일이 벌어지는지는 의견이 분분했다
But what was actually happening as substances warmed or cooled was still hotly debated.
아몽통 같은 이들은
열이 운동의 한 형태이며
The argument of men like Amontons relied completely on the idea
that heat is a form of motion and that particles move more and more closely together
물질을 냉각시키면 입자들이 점점 더
가까워지는 것이라고 굳게 믿었습니다
as the substance in which they're in gets cooler and cooler.
그러나 안타깝게도 냉기의 과학은
이내 커다란 후퇴를 겪게 된다
Unfortunately, the science of cold was about to suffer a serious setback.
입자들의 움직임이 느려지는 현상이
곧 냉각이라는 이론이 밀려나게 된 것이다
The idea that cooling was caused by particles slowing down began to go out of fashion.
열과 냉기에 관한 새로운 경쟁 이론이
18세기 말에 등장했는데
At the end of the 18th century, a rival theory of heat and cold emerged
매우 그럴듯해 보이지만
완전히 틀린 이론이었기 때문이다
that was tantalizingly appealing, but completely wrong.
이것은 '칼로릭 이론'으로,
It was called the 'caloric theory',
프랑스의 위대한 화학자
앙투안 라부아지에가 적극 주장했다
and its principal advocate was the great French chemist Antoine Lavoisier.
당대 대부분의 과학자들처럼, 그는
사비로 연구를 할만큼 부유한 귀족이었다
Like most scientists of the time, Lavoisier was a rich aristocrat who funded his own research.
라부아지에의 부인은
실험 조수 역할을 맡기도 했는데
He and his wife, Madame Lavoisier, who assisted with his experiments,
이들 부부는 유명한 화가 다비드에게
초상화를 부탁할 정도였다
even commissioned the celebrated painter David to paint their portrait.
라부아지에는 질량이 없는
'칼로릭'이라는 유체(流體)가
Lavoisier carried out experiments to support the erroneous idea
열의 실체라는, 이 잘못된 이론을
입증하기 위해 실험을 했다
that heat was a substance, a weightless fluid, that he called 'caloric'.
그는 고체의 경우 분자들이
빽빽하게 모여 있다고 생각했습니다
He thought, in the solid state of matter, molecules were just packed close in together,
여기에 칼로릭을 주입하면
and when you added more and more caloric to this,
칼로릭이 분자들 사이에 스며들어
결합을 헐겁게 한다는 것이죠
the caloric would insinuate itself between these particles of matter and loosen them up.
칼로릭은 이처럼 '스스로 반발하는'
속성을 가진 유체라는 개념이었습니다
So the basic notion was that caloric was this fluid that was, as he put it, 'self-repulsive'.
입자들을 이리저리 흐트러뜨리는
성질을 가지고 있다는 것입니다
It just tended to break things apart from each other.
이것이 그가 생각한
열의 기본 개념입니다
And that's his basic notion of heat.
즉, 냉기는 칼로릭의 부재 또는
칼로릭의 상대적 부족이라고 본 것이죠
So cold is just the absence of caloric, or the relative lack of caloric.
라부아지에는 칼로릭의 양을 재는
칼로리미터라는 기구까지 만들었다
Lavoisier even had an apparatus to measure caloric, which he called a calorimeter.
바깥 용기를 얼음으로 채우고
He packed the outer compartment with ice.
안쪽에는 열원을 넣었다
Inside he conducted experiments that generated heat,
열원은 화학 반응이거나
또는 동물일 때도 있었는데
sometimes from chemical reactions, sometimes from animals,
여기에서 방출되는
칼로릭의 양을 측정하려 했다
to determine how much caloric was released.
얼음이 녹아 나온 물을 모아
그 무게를 달아서
He collected the water from the melting ice and weighed it
열원으로부터 나온
칼로릭의 양을 계산했다
to calculate the amount of caloric generated from each source.
매우 인상적인 것은
라부아지에가
I think the most striking thing about Lavoisier is that
칼로릭을 보통의 물질과 다름없는
하나의 물질로 취급했다는 것입니다
he sees caloric as a substance which is exactly comparable with ordinary matter,
그가 정리한 물질 원소들의 목록에
칼로릭을 포함시켰을 정도이니까요
to the point that he includes caloric in his list of the elements.
로버트 폭스 - 옥스포드 대학
열을 유체 물질로 생각하고
그 양을 따지는 것은 쉽습니다
It's very easy to talk about the quantity of heat and to think of it as a fluid,
반면에 (아몽통의) 경쟁 이론은
열을 물질 입자의 진동으로 보았는데
whereas to talk about the quantity of heat and to think of it as vibration of the particles of matter,
이것은 개념적으로
훨씬 더 어려웠습니다
which was the other alternative, that's much more difficult conceptually.
(칼로릭 이론은) 반증하기가
대단히 어려운 모델이죠
It's a very hard model to refute,
질량도 없는 어떤 물질의 존재를
가정하고 있기 때문입니다
because if you can accept that there is a substance that doesn't have any weight.
라부아지에에게 칼로릭은
엄연한 원소였습니다
Indeed for Lavoisier, heat, caloric, is an element.
산소, 질소 같은
물질 원소 중 하나라는거죠
It's an element like oxygen or nitrogen.
그러니까 산소 기체는
산소와 칼로릭이 합쳐진 것이고
Oxygen gas is made of oxygen plus caloric.
여기에서 칼로릭을 제거하면
산소가 액화된다, 이런 식입니다
If you take the caloric away, presumably the oxygen might liquefy.
자유자재로 설명이 가능했기 때문에
이 모델을 반박하기가 참 어려웠습니다
So it's a very hard model to shift, because it explains so much.
사실, 이 이론만 빼면 라부아지에는
엄청나게 성공한 화학자였죠
And indeed, Lavoisier's chemistry was so otherwise extraordinarily successful.
하지만 라부아지에의
칼로릭 이론은 곧 무너졌습니다
However, Lavoisier's story about caloric was soon undermined.
라부아지에가 틀렸다고 확신하고
There was one man who was convinced Lavoisier was wrong
칼로릭 이론을 논파하겠다고
나선 사람이 있었는데
and was determined to destroy the caloric theory.
그의 이름은 카운트 럼포드이다
His name was Count Rumford.
카운트 럼포드는
다채로운 이력의 소유자였다
Count Rumford had a colorful past.
미국 태생인 그는 미국 독립 전쟁 때
영국측 스파이로 활동했고
He was born in America, spied for the British during the Revolution,
국외 추방 당한 뒤로는
바이에른 왕국의 정부 요직에 올랐다
and after being forced into exile, became an influential government minister in Bavaria.
그가 맡은 임무들 중 하나는
대포와 관련된 연구였는데,
Among his varied responsibilities was the artillery works.
이 연구를 하던 1790년대에
And it was here in the 1790's that he began to think about
대포 천공(穿孔) 작업에서 착안해
칼로릭 이론을 반박할 아이디어를 떠올렸다
how he might be able to disprove the caloric theory using cannon boring.
럼포드는 포신 구멍을 파낼 때
많은 마찰열이 나온다는 점에 주목하고
Rumford had noticed that the friction from boring out a cannon barrel generated a lot of heat.
그 열량을 측정하는
실험을 하기로 마음먹었다
He decided to carry out experiments to measure how much.
가능한 한 많은 열을
만들어내기 위하여
He adapted the machine to produce even more heat
뭉툭하게 생긴 천공기를 설치하고
그 반대쪽 끝은 물에 담가 두었다
by installing a blunt borer that had one end submerged in a jacket of water.
천공기로 포신을 뚫으면
마찰열로 데워진 물은 결국 끓게 된다
As the cannon turned against the borer,
the temperature of the water increased, and eventually, boiled.
천공 작업을 오래 할수록
더 많은 열이 발생했다
The longer he bored, the more heat was produced.
그가 얻은 결론은,
열은 운동의 형태이며
For Rumford, what this showed was that heat must be a form of motion,
그리고 열은 물질이
아니라는 것입니다
and heat is not a substance because you could generate
포신을 돌리면 돌리는대로
끝없이 열이 발생하기 때문이죠
indefinitely large amounts of heat simply by turning the cannon.
럼포드의 노력에도 불구하고
Despite Count Rumford's best efforts,
칼로릭 이론은 18세기 말까지도
가장 우세한 이론이었다
Lavoisier's caloric theory remained dominant until the end of the 18th century.
명성이 드높았던 라부아지에의 이론에
도전하기는 쉽지 않았던 것이다
His prestige as a scientist meant that few dared challenge his ideas.
그러나 그는 불행히도 프랑스 혁명의
소용돌이로부터 자유롭지 못했으며
Sadly, this did not protect him from the revolutionary turmoil in France
연구에도 방해를 받았다
which was about to interrupt his research.
그는 공포 정치 와중에 체포되어
결국 단두대의 이슬로 사라졌다
At the height of the Reign of Terror, Lavoisier was arrested and eventually guillotined.
라부아지에가 단두대에 오른 것은
과학적 이유에서가 아니라
The reason he was guillotined was not because of his science,
프랑스 정부의 국세청 민영화에서
핵심 인물이었기 때문입니다
but because he helped to run the privatized income tax service of the French state.
프랑스에서도 역시나 민영 세금징수원은
가장 미움받는 대상이었던 거죠
There's nothing more unpopular even in France than a privatized tax collector.
라부아지에가 죽은 다음,
그의 아내는 프랑스를 떠나
Once he was guillotined, his wife left France and..
이윽고 1800년대 초반 서유럽으로 온
럼포드를 만났습니다
eventually met Rumford, when he moved to Western Europe in the early 1800's.
그리고 둘은 결혼했죠
Rumford then married her.
럼포드는 자신이 무너뜨린 이론을
만든 남자의 미망인과 결혼한 겁니다
So he'd married the widow of the man who'd founded the theory that he'd destroyed.
결혼은 오래 가지 않았다
The marriage was short-lived.
괴로운 나날을 보낸 럼포드는
라부아지에 부인을 떠나
After a tormented year, Rumford left Madame Lavoisier
그의 첫사랑이라 할 수 있는
과학에 여생을 바쳤다
and devoted the rest of his life to his first love, science.
열과 냉기에 관한 그의 이론이 마침내
인정되기까지는 거의 50년이 걸렸다
It would be nearly 50 years before his theory of heat and cold was finally accepted.
럼포드는 왕립 연구소를 설립하여
과학 연구를 꾸준히 지원했고
A founder of the Royal Institution, Rumford continued to support the pursuit of science,
냉기의 정복을 향한 다음번 커다란 진전이
바로 이곳에서 이루어졌다
and it was here that the next major breakthrough in the conquest of cold would occur.
후일 전자기학 연구로 유명해진
마이클 패러데이가
Michael Faraday, who later became famous for his work on electricity and magnetism,
무심코 했던 실험이 절대 영도를 향한
대장정의 시작이 되었다
unwittingly carried out an experiment that would begin the long descent towards absolute zero.
이제 막 발견된 염소 기체의 성질에
관한 연구가 그에게 맡겨졌다
(화학자 험프리 데이비의 조수였던 시절)
He was asked to explore the properties of newly discovered pungent gas called chlorine.
아마 폭발 위험이 있는 실험이어서
패러데이에게 남겨졌던 것 같다
This experiment was potentially explosive, which is perhaps why it was left to Faraday,
그리고 같은 이유에서 쉬들로 박사도
이 실험을 재현하고 싶어한다
and perhaps also why Dr. Andrew Szydlo is curious to repeat it today.
지금 하려는 실험은
대단히 위험합니다
We are about to undertake an exceedingly dangerous experiment
1823년, 마이클 패러데이는
이 물질을 가열했죠
in which Michael Faraday, in 1823, heated this substance here,
밀봉한 시험관에 담긴
염소 수화물입니다
the hydrate of chlorine, in a sealed tube.
- 밀봉됐습니까?
- 네, 됐습니다
- Is that sealed?
- That's sealed, Andrew.
아주 훌륭해요
That's absolutely brilliant.
원래의 실험에서, 패러데이는
밀봉된 관을 가지고
In the original experiment, Faraday took the sealed tube
결정(結晶)이 들어 있는
한쪽 끝을 가열했다
and heated the end containing the crystals.
그리고 반대편 끝은
얼음에 담갔다
He put the other end in an ice bath.
그는 곧 노란색 염소 가스가
생겨나는 것을 보았다
Soon, he noticed yellow chlorine gas being given off.
기체가 생겨나기 때문에
압력이 올라갑니다
Because the gas is being produced, pressure's building up.
그런데 반대편 끝은
아주 차갑기 때문에
But because this side is so very cold, hopefully what we'll see is
액체 염소 방울이 맺힐 것으로
기대할 수 있습니다
some tiny oily droplets of liquid chlorine being produced.
압력 때문에
일어나는 현상이죠
It's the pressure which is causing this.
지금부터가 위험합니다
Ray, this is where it starts to get dangerous.
이제 몇발짝 뒤로 물러나서..
So if you now take a few steps back..
패러데이의 실험실을 방문한
패리스 박사가 이 실험을 참관했다
When Faraday did the experiment, a visitor, Dr. Paris, called in to see what he was up to.
패리스는 관 바닥 쪽에
기름기가 있다고 지적했다
Paris pointed out some oily matter in the bottom of the tube.
패러데이도 호기심이 생겨
관을 깨뜨려 살펴보기로 했다
Faraday was curious, and decided to break open the tube.
자, 이 안쪽을 한번 보세요
Right, so let's have a look inside here.
폭발과 함께 유리 파편이 날렸다
The explosion sent shards of glass flying.
압력이 갑자기 낮아지면서
기름기 있는 액체는 사라졌다
With the sudden release of pressure, the oily liquid vanished.
- 지금처럼..
- 이런 일이 있었다는거죠?
- And there we are..
- Is that what happened?
네, 정확히 이 현상이었습니다.
펑 터지면서 유리가 날리고..
Yeah, that's exactly what happened. It popped open, glass flew..
염소 기체의
강한 냄새가 느껴지죠?
And can you detect the strong smell of chlorine?
- 네
- 패러데이도 이 냄새를 맡았죠
- I can now.
- Absolutely. Well, he detected the strong smell of chlorine.
그는 여기서 강한 의문을
제기했습니다
And this was a major mystery for him.
패러데이는 밀봉된 관 내부의
압력이 증가했기 때문에
Faraday soon realized the increased pressure inside the sealed tube
기체가 액화된 것임을
곧 알아냈다
had caused the gas to liquefy.
그리고는 똑같은 기법을 활용해
암모니아 기체를 액화시켜 보았다
Later, he used the same technique to liquefy ammonia gas.
그는 압력이 낮아지면서
액체가 기화할 때
He noticed that on releasing the pressure the liquid evaporated,
급격하게 온도가 떨어지는
현상에 주목했다
triggering a dramatic drop in temperature.
패러데이는 언젠가 이런 냉각 기술이
유용하게 쓰일거라고 예측했다
He predicted that one day this cooling might be useful.
암모니아를 이용한
이러한 냉각 기술이
There is great reason to believe that this cooling technique with ammonia
육류나 야채 등의
식료품을 보관하는데
may be successfully employed for the preservation of
효과적으로 이용될 수 있다고
믿을만한 충분한 이유가 있다.
animal and vegetable substances for the purposes of food.
하지만 암모니아를 냉매로 쓴다는
그의 발상은 시대를 앞선 것이었다
But Faraday's ideas of using ammonia as a refrigerant was ahead of its time.
뿐만 아니라, 그는
상업적 활용에는 관심이 없었다
Besides, he had no interest in commercial exploitation.
한편, 대서양 건너 미국의 한 사업가는
전혀 다른 철학을 갖고 있었다
Across the Atlantic, a Yankee entrepreneur had a very different philosophy
그는 냉기를 상업화할 계획이었다
and was about to commercialize cold.
프레더릭 튜더는
그의 형과 이야기를 하다가
Frederic Tudor had a chance conversation with his brother
훗날 미국 최고의 부호가 될
기회를 붙잡았다
that led him on a path to become one of the richest men in America.
저녁 식사 중에
이런 이야기가 나왔던 겁니다
The story goes: at the dinner table, they were trying to decide
아버지가 물려주신 농장으로
어떻게 돈을 벌 수 있을까..
what they had on their father's farm they could make money off of, and..
데니스 피카르 - 스토로우타운 박물관
농장에 바윗덩이들은 넘쳐났지만
누가 그걸 돈 주고 사겠어요
certainly there was a lot of rocks, but people weren't going to pay for that.
그럼 혹시 얼음은 어떨까, 했던거죠.
얼음을 구하기 힘든 지역도 있었으니까요
So they came up with the idea of maybe ice, because some of the areas did not have ice.
터무니없는 생각 같았지만,
결국 대박을 터뜨렸죠
And it seemed kind of crazy at first, but it paid off.
뉴잉글랜드 지방의 호수에서
얼음을 캐내기 시작하면서
When Tudor began harvesting ice from New England ponds
그는 많은 수요를 충당하려면
특화된 도구가 필요함을 곧 깨달았다
he soon realized he needed specialized tools to keep up with the huge demand.
옛날식 나무톱을 개선한
톱을 사용했습니다
We had the saws, and the saws were an improvement over the old wood saws.
양날이 달린 톱인데
They have teeth that are sharpened on both sides and set,
위로나 아래로나
매번 톱질마다 자를 수 있죠
so it cuts on both the up and the down stroke.
혼자서도 약 12000 제곱미터의 면적을
이틀 정도면 거뜬히 파낼 수 있었죠
A crew could clear a three-acre pond easily in a couple of days.
어느 곳에나 얼음을 공급하겠다는
튜더의 꿈은 뉴잉글랜드를 벗어나
Tudor's dream to make ice available to all was not confined to New England.
미국 남부와 캐리비안 등
더운 지방까지 확장하려고 했다
He wanted to ship ice to hot parts of the world like the Caribbean and the Deep South.
튜더가 상선의 선장들에게
얼음을 선적하도록 설득하니까
When Tudor first tried to convince shipmasters to put his load of frozen water into the ships,
물에 떠다니는 배가 왜 물을 싣냐며
모두들 거부했습니다
they all refused because they told him that water belonged outside the hull, not inside.
그래서 직접 배를 사서 쓰려고
자금을 투자 받았죠
So he had to go find other investors to get the money to buy his own ship.
그는 배를 사들여
'The Favorite'으로 명명했습니다
And he bought a ship by the name of The Favorite.
뉴잉글랜드 지방은
세계의 냉동고가 되어
New England became the refrigerator for the world
캐리비안, 남미 해안, 유럽까지
얼음을 공급했고
with ice shipments to the Caribbean, the coast of South America and Europe.
심지어 인도와 중국까지 달했다
Tudor even reached India and China.
월든 호수에서 얼음을 캐는 광경을 보며,
헨리 소로*는 자기가 한때 물놀이를 했던 물이
* '월든'이라는 책으로 유명한 자연주의 문인
Watching the ice cutters working Walden Pond,
Henry Thoreau marveled that water from his bathing beach
지구를 반 바퀴 돌아 동인도까지
이르는 모습에 경탄을 금치 못했다
was traveling halfway around the globe
to end up in the cup of an East Indian philosopher.
튜더는 곧 '얼음왕'이라는
칭호를 얻었으며,
Tudor, who soon became known as the 'Ice King',
늘어나는 얼음 수요를
충족시키기 위해
began using horses and huge teams of workers
말과 대규모 노동력을 동원하여
더욱더 큰 호수들을 캐냈다
to harvest larger and larger lakes, as the demand for ice grew.
19세기 후반이 되자
During the latter half of the 19th century,
얼음 산업 종사자는
수만명에 달했다
the ice industry eventually employed tens of thousands of people.
튜더는 최대의 얼음 공급자이며
Tudor became the largest distributor of ice
미국 최초의 백만장자 가운데
한 명이 되었습니다
and he became one of the first American millionaires.
캐리비안으로 가는 배 한 척마다
그는 6천달러의 수익을 얻었는데
And we're talking about one of his ships going to the Caribbean giving him a profit of $6000.
1년 가계 소득 평균이
2~3백달러였던 시대임을 감안하면
Now, this is in a time period when people were earning $200 to $300 a year - the average family.
단번에 수천달러를 번다는건
상상을 초월하는 수준이었죠
so someone earning thousands of dollars was just inconceivable.
수송 중에 얼음의 20%가
손실되는데도 이 정도였으니
And that would be losing 20 percent of your ice when it got there.
아무튼 막대한 수익인 겁니다
There was still huge amounts of profit.
튜더의 성공을 가능케 한 것은
얼음의 특별한 물리적 성질이었다
Tudor's success was based around an extraordinary physical property of ice.
얼음을 녹이는데 필요한 열량은
It takes the same amount of heat to melt a block of ice
같은 양의 물을 섭씨 약 80도까지
가열하는데 필요한 열량과 같다
as it does to heat a similar quantity of water to around 80 degrees centigrade.
따라서 더운 지방으로 보내더라도
얼음이 녹는데는 긴 시간이 걸린다
This meant that ice took a long time to melt, even when shipped to hotter climates.
구멍가게 수준으로 시작했던 일이
전세계적인 사업이 되었다
What started out as a small family enterprise turned into a global business.
프레더릭 튜더가
냉기를 산업화시킨 일은
Frederic Tudor had industrialized cold
증기기관의 개척자들이
열의 힘을 동력화한 것에 비견된다
in the same way the great pioneers of steam had harnessed heat.
1830년대에 이르러
산업 혁명은 절정에 달했다
By the 1830's, the industrial revolution was in full swing.
아이러니하게도, 증기기관이
열을 운동으로 전환하는 원리를
Yet ironically, it was not until a small group of scientists worked out
일군의 과학자들이
자세히 밝혀낸 후에야
the underlying principles of how steam engines convert heat into motion,
냉기의 정복을 향한
다음 단계가 열리게 되었다
that the next step in the conquest of cold could be made.
열기관의 비밀을 푼 다음에야
Only after solving this riddle of heat engines,
비로소 냉동 기계를
만들 수 있었던 것이다
could the first cold engines be made to produce artificial refrigeration.
"주어진 열량으로부터, 최대한
뽑아낼수 있는 일의 양은 얼마인가?"
"How much useful work can you get out of a given amount of heat?"
이것이야말로, 1800년대 초 유럽 경제의
단연코 가장 중요한 문제가 되었습니다
By the early 1800's, that had become the single most important economic problem in Europe.
열의 낭비를 줄이고 높은 효율로
열을 운동으로 전환하여
To make a profit was to convert heat into motion efficiently
최대한의 기계적 에너지를 얻어내야
높은 수익을 얻을 수 있었습니다
without wasting heat and getting the maximum amount of mechanical effect.
이 문제에 본격적으로 달려든
최초의 인물은
The first person to really engage with this problem
프랑스의 젊은 포병 기술자
사디 카르노였다
was a young French artillery engineer, Sadi Carnot.
그는 증기기관의 효율을 향상시켜
He thought that improving the efficiency of steam engines
워털루 전투에서 패배한 프랑스의
휘청거리는 경제를 살리려고 힘썼다
might help France's flagging economy after the defeat at Waterloo.
프랑스 국립기술교육원에서 일하면서
Working at the Conservatoire des Arts et Metiers,
그는 증기기관이 열을 운동으로
전환하는 원리를 분석했다
he began to analyze how a steam engine was able to turn heat into mechanical work.
제가 생각하기에
카르노의 독창성의 핵심은
The originality of Carnot's treatment, in my eyes, is essentially that
열기관을 이용하여
기계적 에너지를 끌어내려면
he shows that in order to extract energy, to extract work from a heat engine,
높은 온도의 열원,
즉 보일러죠.. 그리고
you need a high temperature source, which is the boiler,
낮은 온도의 부분,
응축기가 필요하다는 겁니다
and you need a lower temperature, which is that of the condenser.
카르노에 의하면
열기관의 핵심 요소는
And the essence of the heat engine for Carnot is that
높은 온도의 보일러로부터
낮은 온도의 응축기로 흐르는 열입니다
heat passes from the high temperature of the boiler
to the lower temperature of the condenser.
관찰해보면, 열이 증기기관 내에서
순환하는 것을 알 수 있습니다
In steam engines, it looks as though heat is flowing around the engine,
열이 이렇게 순환함에 따라
기관은 기계적인 일을 만들어내죠
and as it flows, the engine does mechanical work.
이것이 의미하는 바는,
열이 소모되거나 사라지지 않고
The implication there is that heat is neither consumed nor destroyed.
그저 계속 돌고 돌 뿐인데도
동력이 나온다는 사실이죠
You simply circulate it around, and it does work.
이쯤에서 증기기관의 열을
물레방아의 물에 비유할 수 있겠죠
So there the analogy would be between heat in a steam engine and water in a water wheel.
즉, 증기기관에서는
열의 흐름이 일을 만들어냅니다
as though it's the flow of heat that is actually getting the work done in a standard steam engine.
카르노는 이러한 열의 흐름을
물레방아에서 물의 흐름에 비유했다
Carnot likened this flow of heat to the flow of water over a water wheel.
그는 물레방아가 하는 일의 크기가
물의 낙차에 좌우된다는 점에 주목했다
He saw that the amount of mechanical work produced depended on how far the water fell.
그리고 증기기관도 유사할 것이라는
기발한 아이디어를 내놓았다
His novel idea was that steam engines worked in a similar way,
뜨거운 부분과 차가운 부분의
온도차가 물의 낙차에 해당된다
except this fall was a fall in temperature from the hottest to the coldest part of the engine.
온도차가 크면 클수록
더 많은 일이 만들어진다
The greater the temperature difference, the more work was produced.
카르노는 이 아이디어를 다듬어
일반인을 위한 쉬운 책으로 써냈는데,
Carnot distilled these profound ideas into an accessible book for general readers,
그때문에 명작으로 평가받기는 커녕
과학자들 사이에서는 거의 외면당했다
which meant it was largely ignored by scientists instead of being heralded as a classic.
이 책입니다.
카르노의 유일한 저작이죠
Well this is the book. It's Carnot's only publication,
'열에 의한 동력에 관한 고찰'..
1824년, 118쪽의 작은 책입니다
'Reflections on the Motive Power of Fire' - 1824, a small book, 118 pages only,
겨우 600부만 출판되었고, 카르노가
죽기 전까지는 완전히 묻혀 있었습니다
published just 600 copies, and in his own lifetime it's virtually unknown.
출판된지 20년이 지나서,
스코틀랜드 물리학자 윌리엄 톰슨이
Twenty years after the publication, William Thomson, the Scottish physicist,
이 책을 구하려고 이곳 파리에서
백방으로 수소문했죠
is absolutely intent on finding a copy. He's here in Paris..
사료에 따르면, 그는 한참동안
이 책의 행방을 찾으려고
and the accounts we have suggest that
he spends a great deal of time visiting book shops..
서점을 돌고, 여기 세느 강변의
헌책방 장수들에게 묻고 다녔는데
visiting the bookinistes on the banks of the Seine..
looking, always asking for the book.
돌아오는 답은.. 그런 책은
들어본 적도 없다는 말 뿐이었죠
And the booksellers tell him they've never even heard of it.
윌리엄 톰슨은 나중에
켈빈 경이라는 칭호를 얻었으며
Back then, William Thomson, who would later become Lord Kelvin,
열역학이라는 이 새로운 분야의
거장이 되었다
a giant in this new field of thermodynamics, was impressed by Carnot's idea
그는 열의 순환으로 일이 만들어진다는
카르노의 아이디어에 매료되었다
that the movement of heat produced useful work in the machine.
그런데 파리에서 돌아온 그는
But when he returned home, he heard about an alternative theory
맨체스터의 양조업자 제임스 줄의
또다른 이론에 대해 듣게 된다
from a Manchester brewer called James Joule.
줄은 열의 '이동'만으로
일이 생겨난다는
Joule had this notion that Carnot was wrong -
카르노의 아이디어가
잘못됐다고 생각하고
that heat wasn't producing work just by its movement,
열이 일로 '변환'되는
것이라고 주장했습니다
heat was actually turning into mechanical work,
생각해 보면 이것은
매우 생소한 발상입니다
which is a very strange idea when you think about it.
지금의 우리는 에너지가 여러 형태로
변환된다는 개념에 익숙하지만,
We're all now used to thinking about energy and how it can take all different forms.
열과 기계적 에너지가
궁극적으로 동일하다는 주장은
But it was a revolutionary idea that heat and something like mechanical energy were..
당시로서는 혁명적인 것이었죠
at bottom, the same kind of thing.
그는 자신의 양조장에서 한 실험으로
이러한 이론을 확신하게 되었는데
The experiment that convinced Joule of this was set up in the cellar of his brewery.
증기기관과 반대로, 기계적 운동을
열로 변환시키는 실험 장치였다
It converted mechanical movement into heat, almost like a steam engine in reverse.
무게추를 낙하시키고, 그 힘으로
통 안에 든 물을 휘젓는다
He used falling weights to drive paddles around the drum of water.
이때 일어나는 마찰에 의해
아주 적게나마 열이 발생한다
The friction from this process generated a minute amount of heat.
기계적인 일에 의해 발생하는
이 미미한 온도 증가는
Only brewers had thermometers accurate enough to register this tiny temperature increase
양조업자들이 쓰는 온도계로나
정확히 측정할 수 있었다
caused by a measured amount of mechanical work.
줄의 실험은
커다란 의의를 지닙니다
Joule's work mattered, because it was the first time
기계적 운동과 열 사이의
변환 비율을
that anyone had convincingly measured
믿을만한 정확도로 측정한
최초의 실험이었기 때문이죠
the exchange rate between movement and heat.
그는 운동과 열 사이에 뭔가가
변환된다는 것을 확증했고
He proved the existence of something that converts between heat and motion.
그 뭔가는 나중에 '에너지'라는
이름을 얻게 됐죠
That something was going to be called 'energy'.
바로 그 이유로 인해,
국제 단위계의 에너지 단위가
And it's for that reason that the basic unit of energy
그의 이름을 따서
'줄(joule)'로 명명되었습니다
in the new international system of units is named after him, the Joule.
겉보기에 상충되는
줄과 카르노의 이론은
This apparent contradiction between Joule and Carnot was eventually resolved by Thomson
나중에 톰슨에 의해
'열역학 법칙'으로 통합되었다
in what would later become known as the 'laws of thermodynamics'.
줄의 연구로부터 나온
열역학 제 1법칙은
The first law, from Joule's work, states that
에너지는 다른 형태로
변환될 수 있으나
energy can be converted from one form to another,
새로 생겨나거나 사라지지는
않는다는 것이다
but can never be created or destroyed.
카르노의 이론에서 나온
열역학 제 2법칙은
The second law, from Carnot's theory, states that
열은 온도가 높은 곳에서
낮은 곳으로만 흐른다는 것이다
heat flows in one direction only, from hot to cold.
19세기 후반에 이르러,
에너지라는 이 새로운 개념은
In the second half of the 19th century, this new concept of energy
증기력을 활용한
인공 냉각 장치를 가능하게 했다
paved the way for steam power to artificially produce cold.
현대식 냉장고이든,
증기력을 이용한 얼음 제조기이든,
The flow of heat from hot to cold drives any refrigeration site,
냉각 기술이 이용되는 곳에서는
고온부에서 저온부로 열이 흐른다
whether it's a modern fridge, or a steam-powered ice making machine.
우선, 거대한 피스톤이 암모니아 기체를
압축시켜 뜨거운 액체로 만든다
In the first stage of this cycle, gigantic pistons compress ammonia gas into a hot liquid.
고온의 암모니아 액체는
펌프에 의해 응축기로 유입되고,
The hot liquefied ammonia is pumped into a condenser..
응축기에서 냉각된 다음..
where it is cooled..
물탱크 아래의 파이프로
흘러들어간다
and fed into pipes beneath the water tanks.
다음 단계로, 액체 암모니아가
기화하면서 온도가 떨어진다
In the next stage, the liquid ammonia evaporates, and the temperature drops.
암모니아가 주변의 물로부터
열을 흡수하면서
As the ammonia absorbs heat from the surrounding water,
물탱크에는 서서히
얼음덩어리들이 만들어진다
gradually the tanks of water become blocks of ice.
1880년대에는 미국 전역에
이같은 얼음 공장들이 생겨나서
By the 1880's, many towns across America had ice plants like this one,
하루에 150톤의 얼음을
만들 수 있었다
which could produce 150 tons of ice a day.
인공적으로 만들어진 얼음이
For the first time, artificially produced ice was threatening
처음으로 프레더릭 튜더의
자연빙 산업을 위협했다
the natural ice trade created by Frederic Tudor.
미국인들의 얼음 사랑은
그칠 줄 몰랐다
America's appetite for ice was insatiable.
도살장, 양조장, 식품 창고 등등
어디서나 얼음이 애용되었다
Slaughter houses, breweries and food warehouses all needed ice.
시카고의 생산 라인에서
도축된 육류가
Animals were disassembled on production lines in Chicago
냉동차에 실려
철도를 따라 운반되었다
and the meat was loaded into ice-cooled box cars to be shipped by railroad.
.. 가축류가 대형 포장 센터를 거쳐
전국의 시장으로 배급됩니다
.. livestock, on its way to the great meat packing centers of the nation, to markets everywhere,
갖가지 종류의 식품이 냉동차에 실려
신속, 안전하게 배달됩니다
food of every sort safely and quickly delivered in refrigerator cars.
수천 마일 떨어진 곳에서 생산된
고기로 만든 신선한 스테이크를
From New York to Los Angeles, restaurants were able to serve fresh steaks
미국의 어느 레스토랑에서나
맛볼 수 있게 되었다
thousands of miles from where their meals once roamed.
과일과 채소를 사시사철
쉽게 구할 수 있게 되면서
As fruit and vegetables became available out of season, urban diets improved
도시인들은 최고 수준의
식생활을 누리게 되었다
making city dwellers the best fed people in the world.
가정의 식품 보존을 위해
And to keep everything fresh at home,
얼음 배달원이 매주
냉장고의 얼음을 갈아 넣었다
the ice man made his weekly delivery to re-charge the refrigerator.
냉장고는 사람들의 생활, 특히
식생활에 엄청난 변화를 불러왔습니다
Refrigeration makes a tremendous difference in people's lives.
First of all, in their diet, what it's possible for them to eat.
탐 샤하트먼 - 작가
이제 식료품점에 매일이 아니라
매주 한번씩만 가도 됐죠
They can go to the store once a week, they don't have to go every day.
가게에서는 전세계 어디에서 나온
식품이든지 구할 수 있게 되었고
They can obtain at that store foods that are from almost anywhere in the world
냉장 수송되어 온 식품은
집에서도 냉장 보관할 수 있었습니다
that have been transported and kept cool, and then they can keep them in their own home.
결국 얼음 배달원은 사라지고,
전기 냉장고가 가정에 보급되었다
Eventually the ice man disappeared, as more and more households bought electric fridges.
전기 냉장고의 기본 원리도
이전의 얼음 제조기와 동일하다
These used the same basic principles as the old ice making machines.
냉매가 기화하며 식품의 열을 빼앗아
뒷편으로 배출시킨다
Heat from the food inside is drained away
by the evaporating coolant and is dumped out the back.
압축-기화-응축 사이클은
전기식 펌프에 의해 돌아간다
The electric pump drives the cycle of compression, evaporation and condensation.
이렇게 해서 냉장고는
윙윙거리게 된 것이다
(이 문장은 책의 제목이기도 함)
And that's how the fridge got its hum.
냉장고는 24시간 돌아가기 때문에
전력 회사들에게도 사랑받았습니다
The electric power companies loved refrigerators because they ran all day and all night.
소모 전력량이 크지는 않아도
계속 켜 두는 물건이니까요
They may not have used that much power for each hour, but they continued to use that.
지방으로 전력 사업을 확충할 때
홍보 방법 중 하나도
So, one of the ways that they sold rural electrification
'집에서도 냉장고를 사용할 수 있다'
라는 것이었죠
was the possibility of having your own refrigerator.
초창기에는 냉장고의 냉동고가
물을 얼리는데만 사용되었다
In the early days, the fridge's icebox was used to freeze water, nothing else.
음식을 냉동시키면 음식맛이
변해버린다고 생각되었기 때문이다
Freezing was seen as having the same damaging effects as frost.
이 고정관념을 완전히
사라지게 만든 사람은
The man who would change this idea forever
클레런스 버즈아이라는
과학자 겸 탐험가였다
was a scientist and explorer called Clarence Birdseye.
버즈아이는 1912년
래브라도*로 탐험을 떠났다
* 캐나다 동부 끝의 반도 지방
In 1912, Birdseye set off on an expedition to Labrador.
그곳은 영하 40도의 혹한이다
And the temperature dropped to 40 degrees below freezing.
버즈아이는 이누이트족에게
얼음낚시를 배웠다
The Inuit had taught Birdseye how to ice fish.
수십 센티미터 두께의 얼음에
구멍을 뚫은 다음
Get a hole in the ice, it could be several feet thick.
도구를 이용해서
물고기를 낚아 올립니다
And the fish with the pole(???) lying down below, bring the fish up.
워낙 기온이 낮아서, 잡은 물고기는
둘러메고 가기도 전에 얼어버렸죠
And as he'd do that, he found that it would freeze in this terribly cold air
almost before they had it shouldered.
이것을 요리하니까, 방금 잡은
생선처럼 맛이 좋았습니다
When you went to cook this fish, it tasted just as good as it's fresh.
이유를 알 수 없었습니다. 집에서
냉동시킨 생선은 맛이 별로인데 말이죠
And he couldn't figure that out, because when he froze fish at home, they would taste terrible.
그래서 그는 집에 돌아와서
So when he got back home, he finally tried to figure out
급속냉동과 일반냉동에
어떤 차이가 있는지 궁리했습니다
what was the difference between this quick freezing and usual freezing.
꼼꼼히 조사한 끝에
그는 차이점을 알아냈다
Under closer examination, he could see what was happening to the fish cells.
천천히 냉동시킬 경우,
커다란 얼음 결정이 생겨서
With slow freezing, large ice crystals formed which distorted and ruptured the cells.
생선의 세포 조직을 파괴시킨다
이것을 해동시키면 조직이 파괴되면서
영양분과 향이 씻겨나가는 것이다
When thawed, the tissue collapsed and all the nutrients and flavor washed away.
'무른 딸기 현상' 이라고도 합니다
That's the 'mushy strawberry syndrome'.
싱싱한 딸기를
냉동실에 넣어 얼렸다가
People food freeze strawberries as they pick and dry them (???),
다음날 먹으려고 보면
죄다 물러 터져 있죠
then they put them out on the table the next day, and they collapse, they're all mushy.
반면, 급속냉동시킬 경우
얼음 결정이 작게 형성되어
But with fast freezing, only tiny ice crystals were formed inside the cells
세포가 별로 파괴되지 않는다
and these caused little damage.
결국 냉동 속도에 달린 것이다
It was all down to the speed of the freezing zone.
버즈아이는 이렇게
급속하게 냉동시킬 수 있다면
What Birdseye found out is, if you can get food to this zone very quickly -
flash freezing or quick freezing,
얼음 결정에 의한
조직 손상이 줄어들어서
you avoid this ice crystallization, and that makes it possible for the food,
다시 녹여 요리를 해도
신선한 재료처럼 맛있다는걸 알아냈죠
when it's unfrozen and cooked, to taste just as good as it's fresh.
원리상으로는 간단했지만,
래브라도에서 경험한 자연적인 과정을
The basic concept was simple, but it took Clarence Birdseye another ten years
상업용 급속냉동 기술로 완벽하게
재현하는데는 10년이 걸렸다
to perfect the commercial fast-freezing technique
that would mimic the natural process he'd experienced in Labrador.
1924년, 버즈아이는 매사추세츠주
글로스터에서 급속냉동 사업을 시작했다
In 1924, he opened a flash freezing plant in Gloucester, Massachusetts
갓 잡은 생선을 영하 45도까지
냉동시키는 창고이다
that froze freshly landed fish at -45 degrees.
그는 이것을 육류, 채소류 등
다른 식료품까지 확장하여
He then extended that to all sorts of other kinds of meats and produce and vegetables,
냉동식품 사업을 사실상
혼자 힘으로 개척했습니다
and almost single-handedly invented the frozen food industry.
냉동/냉장고는 마침내
현대 생활의 상징이 되어갔다
Fridges and freezers would eventually become icons of modern living.
때를 같이 하여,
또다른 형태의 냉각 기술이
But there was a less visible cold transformation happening at the same time.
도시 생활 문화에
막대한 영향을 끼쳤다
This would also have a huge impact on urban living,
공기 자체를 냉각시키는 기술이다
the cooling of the air itself.
드레블이 제임스 왕을 떨게 만들었던
사건으로부터 3세기가 지났다
Three centuries had passed since Cornelius Drebbel had shaken King James in Westminster.
20세기 초엽, 냉방 기술은
이제 전세계를 뒤흔들 참이었다
Now, at the dawn of the 20th century, air cooling was about to shake the world.
이봐, 그 에어컨인가 뭔가 하는게
대체 어떤 거지?
Tell me, what is the lowdown on this air conditioning thing?
자넨 왜 난처하게
그런 걸 물어보나?
Now you've started something by asking me that.
미국인의 생활을 바꾼 냉방 기술의
주역은 윌리스 캐리어이다
Air conditioning was about to transform America.
And the person responsible was Willis Carrier,
그의 기술 혁신이 편안한 냉방 기술의
신화를 만들어냈다
whose important breakthrough passed into comfort cooling mythology.
안개 낀 어느날 밤,
Let's go back to that foggy night,
젊은 기술자 윌리스 캐리어는
어떤 문제에 대해 생각중이었습니다
when a young engineer named Willis Carrier sought the answer to a problem:
산업 생산에 영향을 주는 습도를
어떻게 제어할 수 있을까..
the effects of humidity of moist air on industrial production.
어쩌면 안개에 답이 있을지 모른다
Fog, maybe that's the answer.
생각해 보면..
Let's see..
안개는 수증기가 응축된 것이다
Fog is water vapour that's been condensed.
안개가 만들어지는 것은,
공기가 차가워졌고
That's because the air has become cooler,
찬 공기에도 같은 양의 수증기가
들어있기 때문이다
and cool air kept all this much moisture as warm air.
그럼 마찬가지로,
공기를 냉각시켜서
Maybe that's the way to reduce humidity.
습기를 응축시키면
습도를 낮출 수 있지 않을까?
Cool the air, and condense the moisture.
It might work.
온도를 조절하여 습도를 조절한다,
Control of humidity through control of temperature.
이것이 윌리스 캐리어의
아이디어였습니다
That was Willis Carrier's idea.
1902년, 캐리어는 특별한 임무를 띠고
브루클린으로 파견되었습니다
Carrier is sent to Brooklyn for a very special job in 1902.
당시 미국에서 가장 인기 있던
올컬러 잡지 'Judge'의 출판사로 갔죠
The company that publishes the magazine 'Judge',
그 회사에 아주 큰 문제가
발생했습니다
one of the most popular full-color magazines in America at this particular time,
is having a huge problem.
마샤 애커먼 - 작가
브루클린의 7월 여름 날씨에
It's July in Brooklyn, and the ink for which they..
잡지 표지에 인쇄할 잉크가
자꾸 미끄러져 나갔던 겁니다
which they use on their beautiful covers is sliding off the pages.
습도가 너무 높았기 때문이죠
It will not stick because the humidity is too high.
선풍기 회사의 신입사원 캐리어는
그가 개발중이던 기술을 응용하여
Carrier, using some principles that he's been developing
as a young, new employee of this fan company,
Judge 1902년 7월호를
인쇄해 낼 방도를 찾아냈습니다
finds a way to get out the July of 1902 run of the Judge magazine,
그 길을 시작으로 드디어 자신의
에어컨 왕국을 건설하기 시작했죠
and from there he begins to eventually build his air conditioning empire.
에어컨 수요는 점차 늘어났다
The demand for air conditioning gradually grew.
1920년대에는 영화관이 에어컨의
홍보대사 역할을 했다
In the 1920's, movie houses were among the first to promote the benefits.
여름엔 사람들이 더위를 피하려고
영화관에 몰려들었다
People would flock there in summer to shelter from the heat.
극장은 굉장히 인기있었고
The movies are wildly popular.
에어컨도 관객을 모으는데
분명히 한 몫 했습니다
And the air conditioning certainly helps to attract an audience,
특히나 푹푹 찌는 날엔
극장에 콕 박혀서
especially if they happen to be walking down the street on a horribly hot day,
즐거운 시간을 보낼 수 있었죠
and they duck into this movie theater and have this wonderful experience.
에어컨은 일터에서도
점차 일반화되었다
Air conditioning became increasingly common in the workplace too,
특히 섬유, 담배 공장이 많은
남부 지방에서
particularly in the South, where textile and tobacco factories
냉방은 필수 요건이 되었다
were almost unbearable without cooling.
근로자가 쾌적한 환경에서
좋은 공기를 마실 때
When employees breathe good air and feel comfortable
작업의 품질과 속도도 높아집니다
they work faster and do a better job.
레이먼드 아르세놀 - 남플로리다 대학
노동자들을 위해
시원한 근로 조건을 제공하다니
I think some people think that these were nice, compassionate employers
훈훈한 사장님이로구나 싶겠지만
택도 없는 소리죠
who were cooling down the workplace for the workers,
but of course nothing could be further from the truth.
의도하지 않은 효과였을 뿐이고,
실제로는..
That was an inadvertent byproduct, but actually this was..
섬유가 손상되지 않게 하려는
방적 공장의 품질관리법일 뿐입니다
a quality control device to control the breaking of fibers in cotton mills,
다른 공장에서도
사정은 마찬가지죠
to get consistent quality control in these various industries,
담배 재건조 공장에서는 항상
먼지가 골칫거리였습니다
to control the dust that had bedevilled tobacco stemming room workers for decades.
그리고 제 생각엔
노동자들이 집에 돌아가면
And I think the workers obviously went home and..
냉방 안되는 방에 앉아서
to their un-air-conditioned shacks, in most cases..
낮에 시원한 일터에서 보낸 시간이
더 좋았지, 했을겁니다
and talked about how nice and cool it was working during the day.
이 지방에서 오래 산 사람들도
누구나 그렇겠지만
Well as anybody will tell you who's lived here for very long..
에어컨 천국인 요즘 같은 세상에도
뙤약볕, 땀, 습도는 여전하죠
even today, age of air conditioning, there's still plenty of sun, and sweat, and humidity.
참고 견디는 수 밖에요
It's something you just have to deal with.
큰 돈 안들이고 에어컨을 들여놓으면
더위로 고생할 일이 뭐 있습니까
It's silly to suffer from the heat when you can afford the modest cost of air conditioning.
1950년대에 들어
가정용 에어컨이 보급되었다
By the 1950's, people were air conditioning their homes
쉽게 설치할 수 있는
독립된 실외기가 붙어 있었다
with stand-alone window units that could be easily installed.
이것은 단순한 가전제품이 아니라
새로운 멋진 생활 양식이었다
This wasn't just an appliance. It offered a new, cool way of life.
에어컨 혁명 이전에
남부 지방 마을의 풍경을 보면
Walking down a typical Southern street prior to the air conditioning revolution,
사람들, 가족들이
집 밖에 나와 있었죠
you would've seen families, individuals, outside.
자기집 아니면 이웃집
앞마당에 모여 있었습니다
They would've been on their porches, on each other's porches.
이웃들끼리 자주 오가는
공동체적 전통이죠
There was a visiting tradition, a real sense of community.
에어컨이 이것을
다 바꿔 놓았습니다
Well, I think all that changes with air conditioning, and..
요즘은 주택지를 지나다 보면
you walk down that same street, and basically what you'll hear are
사람들의 대화가 아니라
실외기의 윙윙대는 소리가 들리죠
not the voices of people talking on the porch,
but you'll hear the whir of the compressors.
우리집에 뭐가 생겼게요?
Guess what we've got?
RCA 에어컨이예요
An RCA room air conditioner.
여자인 저는요, 어머니께서
제 방을 먼지 없는 청결한 곳으로
I'm a woman, and I know how much pure air means to mother
만드시려고 얼마나 애쓰시는지
잘 안답니다
in keeping our rooms clean and free from dust and dirt.
냉기를 다스리게 되면서
도시 생활도 바뀌었다
Control of the cold has transformed city life.
냉장 기술의 발달에 의해
Refrigeration helped cities expand outwards
멀리서 생산된 식품도 먹을수 있게 되면서
도시는 넓게 확장했다
by enabling large numbers of people to live at great distances from their source of food.
또한 냉방 기술 덕분에
도시는 위로도 확장되었다
Air conditioning enabled cities to expand upwards.
20층 이상으로는 강풍 때문에
창문을 여닫을 수 없다
Beyond 20 stories, high winds make open windows impractical.
하지만 에어컨의 도움으로
100층짜리 마천루도 가능해졌다
But with air conditioning, 100 story skyscrapers were possible.
새롭게 출현한 이 기술들은
Technologies emerged which not only worked
인간을 냉기의 해악으로부터
막아주는데 그치지 않고
to insulate human society against the evils of cold,
냉기를 생산적이고, 관리 가능하며,
효과적인 자원으로 탈바꿈시켰습니다
but turned cold into a productive, manageable, effective resource.
한편으로는 증기기관,
다른 한편으로는 냉장고..
On the one hand the steam engine, on the other the refrigerator.
19세기의 이 위대한
두 가지 상징물은
Those two great symbols of 19th century world
전세계 경제와 사회를
완전히 바꾸어 놓았습니다
which completely changed the society and economy of the planet.
저는 이 모든 것을
'냉기의 상업화'로 해석합니다
All that is part of, I think, what we could call 'bringing cold to market' -
두려움의 대상이던
유해한 냉기를
turning it from an evil agent that you feared
이윤을 창출하는
자원으로 바꾼 것입니다
into a force of nature from which you could profit.
지난 두 세기 동안의
폭발적인 인구 성장도
The explosive growth of the modern world over the last two centuries
냉기의 정복에 힘입은 바 크다
owes much to the conquest of cold.
그러나 이제까지는 단지
극저온을 향한 여정의 시작이었다
But this is only the beginning of the journey down the temperature scale.
보다 낮은 온도를 얻는 것은
훨씬 더 어렵지만
Going lower would be even harder, but would produce greater wonders
미래의 놀라운 기술 혁신을
가져다 줄 것이다
that promise extraordinary innovations for the future.
결승 테이프를 끊기 위해
과학자들이 경쟁하면서
With rival scientists racing towards the final frontier,
그들의 발은 바빠지고,
분자의 요동은 느려진다
the pace quickens and the molecular dance slows,
마지막 결승선에서
그들을 기다리는 성배는
as they approach the holy grail of cold..
절대 영도이다
absolute zero.
- 2부로 이어집니다 -
딕테이션, 한/영 자막 제작
DCinside 과학갤/다큐갤 '디핑'
croydon.egloos.com